<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plea for the peoples good old cause: Or, The fundamental lawes and liberties of England asserted, proved, and acknowledged, to be our right before the Conquest, and by above 30 Parliaments, and by the late King Charls; and by the Parliament and their army in their severall declarations in their particular streights and differences. By way of answer to Mr. James Harrington his cxx. political aphorismes, in his second edition. By Capt. William Bray.</title>
            <author>Bray, William, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 763[7]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207096</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866168</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">167144</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 167144)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 117:E763[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plea for the peoples good old cause: Or, The fundamental lawes and liberties of England asserted, proved, and acknowledged, to be our right before the Conquest, and by above 30 Parliaments, and by the late King Charls; and by the Parliament and their army in their severall declarations in their particular streights and differences. By way of answer to Mr. James Harrington his cxx. political aphorismes, in his second edition. By Capt. William Bray.</title>
                  <author>Bray, William, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. and are to be sold by Francis Smith at the Elephant and Castle near Temple-Barr.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Entered according to order."</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 17 Oct.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harrington, James, 1611-1677. --  Aphorisms political --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Constitutional history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:167144:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLEA FOR THE PEOPLES GOOD OLD CAVSE: Or, The FUNDAMENTAL Lawes and Liberties of England Aſſerted, proved, and acknowledged, to be Our RIGHT before the CONQUEST, and by above 30 Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and by the late KING <hi>CHARLS;</hi> and by the <hi>PARLIAMENT</hi> and their <hi>ARMY</hi> in their ſeverall Declarations in their particular <hi>Streights</hi> and <hi>Differences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By way of ANSWER To Mr. JAMES HARRINGTON his CXX. Political Aphoriſmes, in his ſecond EDITION.</p>
            <p>By Capt. WILLIAM BRAY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Acts 22.28, 29.</bibl>
               <p>And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid BUT I was <hi>FREEBORNE.</hi> Then straightway they departed from him which ſhould have examined him; And the Chief Captain alſo was afraid, after he knew he was a <hi>Roman,</hi> and becauſe he had bound him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Entered according to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed by</hi> J. C. <hi>and are to be ſold by</hi> Francis Smith <hi>at the</hi> Elephant <hi>and</hi> Caſtle <hi>near</hi> Temple-Barr. 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:167144:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:167144:2"/>
            <p>
               <label>I.</label> AS to the firſt Aphoriſme, it is granted you, that the errours and ſufferings of a People, are from their Governours; But I deſire you to conſider, and grant the Reaſon thereof which is, (as I conceive) becauſe they have laid aſide the RIGHT RULE (<hi>viz.</hi> the FUNDAMENTAL LAW) to be directed, and governed by, and to govern others alſo by, in this grand and humane concernment, as to LIFE, LIMB, LIBERTY and ESTATE, according to the 29th Chapter of the great CHARTER of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>II.</label> As to your ſecond Aphoriſm I averr, That the foundation of the Government of <hi>England</hi> is LAW, and a ſufficient unmoveable Foundation, and is termed a Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Law, not only from the unknown Original of the great Antiquity of it, (by mutual conſent, agreement, and uſage of the People (as is to be preſumed) upon mature and ſerious deliberation, without any violent impoſition) But becauſe of the juſtneſs, peaceableneſs, and impartiality thereof, for the provident means of <hi>conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of all our <hi>Lives, Limbs, Liberties and Estates,</hi> from illegal, and Arbitrary violence, and deſtruction, and to procure Juſtice and Right in the Land of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity; And for the Governours (being generally but temporary, and ſubject to imperfection, death, and divers humane caſualties) they are in the eye of the Law ſubordinate to the being, and Excellency of the Law, neither did ever any wiſe and juſt perſon (as I conceive) who loved his Country) in any age or time, (upon juſt and ſerious conſideration with himſelf (requiſite in ſuch caſes of weight) endeavour to alter it. And if any perſons have laboured an alteration (to gratifie an unjuſt Faction or intereſt, or for ſome other Reaſons preſented (though very plauſible) it hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes proved very fatal to the Innovators themſelves in the experience of the People in the exerciſe of two of the ſences, <hi>(viz.)</hi> of Sight and Feeling, although you ſay in your 5th Aphoriſm, they cannot ſee but feel.</p>
            <p>The 29th Chapter of the <hi>Great Charter</hi> conſiſts of theſe enſuing Particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>1.</label> That no man ſhall be taken or impriſoned in the firſt Place; becauſe the <hi>Liberty</hi> of a mans <hi>Perſon</hi> is more precious to him then all the reſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>2ly.</label> None ſhall be diſſeiſſed (that is diſpoſſeſſed of his Freehold (that is) Lands, or Livelihood, or Liberties, or Free Cuſtoms, (that is) of Franchiſes, Freedomes, and Free Cuſtomes, as belong to him by Free BIRTHRIGHT.</item>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:167144:3"/>
               <item>
                  <label>Thirdly,</label> None ſhall be Out-lawed made an <hi>Exlex,</hi> put out of the Law, (that is) deprived of the benefit of the Law.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Fourthly,</label> None ſhall be exiled or baniſhed out of his Country (that is) no man ſhall looſe his Country.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Fifthly,</label> None ſhall be in any ſort deſtroyed, unleſs it be by the Verdict of his Equals, or according to the Law of the Land.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sixthly,</label> No man ſhall be condempned at the <hi>Kings Suit,</hi> either before the King in his Bench, or before any COMMISSIONER or JUDGE <hi>whatſoever,</hi> but by the lawful Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Peers, (that is, Equals) or according to the Law of the Land.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And further to manifeſt that it is to be preſumed, that the people were ſenſible that there was a poſſibility &amp; probability of imperfection in a King (as he was a man) what through himſelf on the one hand, or what through evil advice on the other hand, which may ſurprize greatneſs and ſeduce it contrary (peradventure ſometimes) to their own inclination, ſuitable to that ſaying of the Apoſtle 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8.10. <hi>If we ſay we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves and the truth is not in us.</hi> If we ſay we have not ſinned, we make him a lyar and his word is not in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9, 10. What then are we better then they? No, in no wiſe: for we have before proved both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that they are all under ſin; As it is written, <hi>There is none righteous no not one.</hi> For no ſingle PERSON or PERSONS in the world that ever did or may Rule among men, can ſay of himſelf or themſelves as <hi>Paul</hi> in the 4 <hi>Heb.</hi> 15. ſaid of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> who though he was tempted yet was <hi>without ſin;</hi> therefore it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary there ſhould be a Legal Supremacy in our <hi>FUNDAMENTAL LAWS</hi> and <hi>RIGHTS,</hi> and to manifeſt (as I conceive) that there was like Knowledge, and neceſſary indubitable apprehention in a King (in the daies of many Monarchs) as well as in the People, that there was ſuch a poſſibility and probability of imperfection if the Law ſhould not be a Rule to the Governours (as well as governed) there is in the end of the ſaid 29th Chapter theſe other and laſt enſuing Legal and neceſſary particulars, and <hi>Obligations,</hi> to bind him from intermedling, and doing Acts of evil, or hindring Acts of Juſtice or Right, and that the Peple in their Methodical Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental way of Juſtice might diſtribute Juſtice, and Mercy one amongſt another, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that RIGHTEOUS RULE 7 <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. <hi>Do in all things as you would be done unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> We ſhall ſell to no man Juſtice or Right; So that Covetouſneſs, (which by the Reverend Apoſtles, and divers Scriptures, is ſaid, to be the Root of all evil) was to be abandoned by this FUNDAMENTAL LAW, and no profit was to ſtand in the way of Right to any man whatſoever.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:167144:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly.</hi> We ſhall deny to no man Juſtice or Right ſo that the Law ſaith, it was not in the power or courteſie of Princes to give us Right as a favour, for they were bound by the Common Law, which was our Right for many hundred years ago before the <hi>CHARTER,</hi> and by the <hi>CHARTER,</hi> and by <hi>OATH,</hi> not to deny us Right, yea impartiall Juſtice or Right. And therefore <hi>VVilliam</hi> the Conquerour after he had Conquered all almoſt, yet did ſweare to confirme, and defend our Lawes, and antient Cuſtomes and Rights.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly.</hi> We ſhall deferr to no man juſtice or Right, ſo that thereby it is apparent, there was no way for Evaſion of this wiſe <hi>CHARTER</hi> of Confirmation or Reſtitution of our Common Law, or to avoyde the injoyment of our Fundamentall Rights (without which we cannot live) For it is a clear thing to all rationall men, that Juſtice or Right is not to be ſold or denyed to any, but if it be neither ſold or denyed (in any viſible Fact or Deed,) yet if it ſhould be delayed, it would be a lingring, and waſting ſpoyle and Conſumption, and as deſtructive to the intereſt of the People, as if the two laſt precedent Proviſions and benefits, had no being at all, for the renowned Lord <hi>Cook</hi> ſaith, <hi>dilatio est quaedam negatio;</hi> And therefore I ſhall ſay as it is ſaid by the Tranſlator to the Reader in the Book called the Mirror of Juſtices, (who rationally declined the opinion of ſome) That our Common Lawes as to the generality flowed firſt out of <hi>Normandy</hi>) As <hi>Cicero</hi> was bold to derive the Pedigree of his Roman Law from the great God <hi>Jupiter,</hi> ſo (ſaith he) I hope without offence, I may be imboldened in the perſon of our Common Law, to ſay, That when the <hi>Lawes</hi> of God and Reaſon came firſt into <hi>England,</hi> then came I in. This I declare, and recite, to ſhew the excellency of the Fundamentall Law of the Nation.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in the firſt part of his <hi>Inſtitutes</hi> in his Commentary upon <hi>Liatle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4 <hi>Sect.</hi> 108. <hi>Magna CHARTA</hi> is ſo called in reſpect of the weightineſs, and weighty greatneſs of the matter contayned in it in few words, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fountaine of all the Fundamentall Lawes of the Realme, and therefore to be preſumed inviolable, and ſaith he, it may be truly ſaid of it, That it is <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in parvo:</hi> It is in our Books called <hi>CHARTA LIBERTATUM. COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MUNIS LIBERT AS Angliae,</hi> or <hi>Libertates Angliae,</hi> or <hi>CHARTA de LIBERTATIBUS, MAGNA CHARTA</hi> confirmed above 30 times in full PARLIAMENT. And by the Statute of the 42 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 3. if any Statute be made againſt it; it ſhall be voyd; whereby it doth appeare by the wiſe Act of our Anceſtors (in former and peaceable times,) that they did foreſee that future Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might poſſiby endeavour to make this Fundamentall Law ineffectuall, by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomthing or other againſt it: And further he ſaith (To demonſtrate Parliaments are, and are juſtly to be limitted, and guided by it, ſo as to make no Act contrary to it, or inconſiſtent with it) It is the FOUNDATION OF ALL OTHER ACTS OF PARLIAMENT: And further he ſaith (to manifeſt that this Law was common Law, and was before the Charter in the peoples poſſeſſion:) It is but a Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Reſtitution of the Common Law, as in the Statute, made <hi>Confirmatio Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum. An.</hi> 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. it appeareth by the opinion of all the Juſtices: And it is a Maxime in the Law, No man ought to be wiſer then the Law, and <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating his affection to the excellent common Law of England had the honorable Title to be ſtiled <hi>Vindex Anglicanae Libertatis,</hi> as appeares by Mr. <hi>John Baſhawes</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:167144:4"/>Argument of Law (in Parliament) againſt the Biſhops Cannons: And likewiſe Mr. Sollicitor St. <hi>Johns</hi> in his Argument of Law againſt the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> ſaith the deſtruction of the Law diſſolves the Arteries, and Ligaments that hold the body to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and cites the Caſe of <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley,</hi> who were beheaded for executing that <hi>ILLEGALL ACT</hi> of <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> 11. H. 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. which gave power to Juſtices of Aſſiſe as well as Juſtices of the Peace <hi>VVithout</hi> any finding or preſentment by Jury of 12 men of the Neighbourhood being the ancient <hi>BIRTH-RIGHT</hi> of the ſubject, upon bare information for the King before them made to have full power, and Authority by their diſcretions to heare and determine all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or contempts committed or done by any perſon or perſons againſt the order, forme, manner or effect, of any Statute made, and not repealed: By colour of which <hi>Act of Parliament SHAKEING</hi> the <hi>FUNDAMENTAL LAVV, viz:</hi> the 29. <hi>cap.</hi> of <hi>Magna CHARTA</hi> it is not credible (ſaith he,) what Exactions and Oppreſſions were done to the dammage of many People, both indicted at Common Law, and by Act of Parliament 21 <hi>H.</hi> 8. both loſt their heads. And the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in the 4th part of his <hi>Institutes,</hi> calls that ACT OF PARLIAMENT A MISCHIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOVS ACT, <hi>with a Flattering Preamble,</hi> The Colour and Fraudulent pretences (to avoyde our <hi>ANTIENT BIRTH-RIGHT, TO DELUDE,</hi> and amuze the People) were to avoyde divers miſchiefs.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To the diſpleaſure of Almighty God.</item>
               <item>2. To the great Let of the Common Law.</item>
               <item>3. The great Let of the wealth of the Land, as high pretences as any (that would make Innovation) can deviſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>It was one of the Principle Treaſons of <hi>Triſilian</hi> cheife Juſtice for dilivering his opinion in ſubverſion of the Law, for which he was deprived of his life: And the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in his Proeme to the ſecond part of his <hi>Institutes,</hi> ſets forth that <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt did ordaine that <hi>Magna CHART A</hi> ſhould be ſent under the great Seale to all Juſtices of the Forreſt as to others, and to all Sheriffs, and to all other Officers, and to all Cityes, and to all Cathedrall Churches, and read and publiſhed in every County foure times in the year in full County, 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. and <hi>cap.</hi> 3. and 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.17. And in the Preamble of the great Charter, as the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> ſhewes in the ſecond part of his <hi>Institutes,</hi> This antient, this Common Law was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto, and confirmed in theſe words in the <hi>CHARTER, viz.</hi> that the King did it <hi>ſpontanea &amp; bona voluntate,</hi> that ſo the King might not plead <hi>per dureſſe,</hi> as King <hi>John</hi> did, who ſought to avoyd it upon pretence of <hi>Dureſs;</hi> And further ſaith the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in his Proeme to the ſecond part of his <hi>Institutes.</hi> The Common <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the great <hi>Charter</hi> cannot be avoyded by the pretence and ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the minority of a King, becauſe his pollitique capacity did alwayes judge him to be of age and no Minor, that no argument whatſoever might avoyde our Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes and Libertyes: And further he ſaith that the onely thing that hath impugned our Liberties, hath been evill Counſel, Flattery, and Ambition, and cites the Caſe of <hi>Hugo de Burgo</hi> cheife Juſtice in <hi>Henry</hi> the 3d, his time, which is above 400 yeares agoe, and <hi>Hugh Spencer,</hi> &amp;c: for giving raſh and evill Counſell to <hi>Ed.</hi> the 2d, but their advice proved deſtructive to them, as the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> that renowned and induſtrious <hi>PATRIOT,</hi> excellently ſhewes and illuſtrates in the ſecond part of his Inſtitutes of the Lawes, of <hi>England</hi> in his Proem, and upon the 29th, Chapter of the great Charter. All which (with friendly ſubmiſſion) (although you are a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:167144:4"/>get to me) to your impartiall, ſerious, and juſt conſideration, is of great uſe, and worthy your reading, and of extending your abilityes, and underſtanding to manifeſt your affections, to thoſe <hi>Fundamentall Legal Aphoriſmes</hi> therein contained, or to be naturally deduced inſtead of your own <hi>Politicall ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further to continue to manifeſt the Excellency of the being and ſupremacy of the <hi>Law</hi> averred, and mutually confeſſed in the dayes of Monarchy, and by honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Parliamentary Counſell, you may ſee in <hi>Raſtalls</hi> Abridgements of the Statutes Title Juſtice and Right Juſtices, <hi>An.</hi> 2. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. By the aſſent of the great men, and otherwiſe men of our Counſell, we have commanded all our Juſtices that they ſhall from hence forth do even <hi>LAVV</hi> and execution of <hi>RIGHT,</hi> to all our Subjects Rich and Poore, without having regard to any Perſon, and without letting to do <hi>RIGHT,</hi> for any <hi>Letters</hi> or <hi>Commandement</hi> which may come to them from <hi>VS,</hi> or from <hi>any other,</hi> or for any other <hi>CAUSE,</hi> ſuitable to this alſo hath all the Kings of <hi>England</hi> been obliged by the Sacred and inviolable Obligation of an Oath, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 6 <hi>Heb.</hi> 16, 17. Men verily ſweare by the greater, and an Oath for Confirmation is to them an end of all Strife, and that God (to ſhew the immutability of his Counſell) confirmed his promiſes by an Oath; And in the firſt Remonſtrance of Parliament, dated the 15th of <hi>December,</hi> 1641. you may find what Particulars were declared as grand evils, Incumbrances, Breaches, and Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces done againſt the Righteous antient <hi>Lawes</hi> and LIBERTIES of the People, which ſhewes what the <hi>GOOD OLD CAUSE</hi> was originally declared to be, in defence of which cauſe there hath been ſhed ſo much precious <hi>Blood, Destruction of FAMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIES,</hi> and many <hi>MILLIONS</hi> of Treaſure ſpent.</p>
            <p>I have been a little tedious in this, partly, becauſe I ſaw an ingenious Pen take ſome juſt Cauſe of offence (as I conceive) from your Petition, directed to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of the Commonwealth, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. cited by Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> in his Book called A <hi>CHRISTIAN CONCERTATION, &amp;c:</hi> your words he cites are theſe, <hi>(viz) Your minds are not ſettled in any known Constitution of Government, or Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Orders, according to which all</hi> LAWS <hi>ſhould be made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The late King <hi>Charls</hi> in his Declaration (publiſhed by advice of his Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, in the Book of Collections of Remonſtrances and Declarations printed by <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Husbands</hi> by Authority of Parliament, <hi>pag.</hi> 28, 29.) ſaith, That the <hi>Law</hi> is the INHERITANCE of every Subject, and the onely ſecurity he can have for his <hi>LIFE, LIBERTY</hi> and <hi>ESTATE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in an anſwer to the Petition of the Houſe of Commons, 28 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1641. <hi>pag.</hi> 61. he called God to witneſs that the <hi>LAVV</hi> and <hi>LIBERTIE</hi> of the Subject ſhould be as much his care, and induſtry as of his life, or of the Lives of his deereſt Children.</p>
            <p>And in the ſaid book of Declarations of Parliament, 19th, <hi>May,</hi> 1642. <hi>pag.</hi> 211.212. We are fully (ſay they) of the Kings mind, that he might reſt ſo ſecure of the affections of his Subjects, That he ſhould not need of Forraigne force to preſerve him from Oppreſſion, and are very confident he ſhould never want an abundant evidence of the good wiſhes and aſſiſtance of the whole Kingdom, eſpecially if he ſhall be pleaſed to hold that <hi>Gratious</hi> reſolution of building upon that ſure FOUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DATION the LAW of the Land. Then their Remonſtrance of Parliament <hi>May</hi> 26. 1642. <hi>pag.</hi> 263. That they would be tender of the LAW, which they acknowledged
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:167144:5"/>be the <hi>Safeguard</hi> of all <hi>PUBLICK</hi> and <hi>PRIVATE</hi> Intereſts. And page 657 and 666, That the Parliament raiſed the Army for their juſt defence and LAWS NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CESSARY PRESERVATION when an Army was marching towards them to deſtroy them both. And in the Book of the Declarations of the Army Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Matthew Simmons</hi> 27, <hi>Sept.</hi> 1647. After their then victory, they hoped to to put an end to Tyranny and Oppreſſions, that Juſtice and Equity according to the LAW of the LAND ſhould have beee done to the People, That the meaneſt Subject ſhould fully enjoy his RIGHT, LIBERTIE and PROPRIETY in all things which the Parliament had made known to all the world in divers of their Declarations, to which they had ſo often bound themſelves to perform by their OATHS, VOWS, COVENANTS, &amp; PROTESTATIONS, and the Parliament in the aforeſaid Book of Declarations, page 659, 666, 661, amongſt other words declared that the <hi>Cauſe</hi> was, That the Commonalty might enjoy (in the maintenance of their <hi>LAVVS, LIBERTY. RELIGION,</hi> their own <hi>BIRTH-RIGHTS, FREEDOM</hi> and <hi>LIBERTY</hi> of the <hi>LAVVS</hi> of the <hi>LAND,</hi> being equally intituled thereunto, with the greateſt Subject, yet we hope (ſay they) this is far from any purpoſe, to raiſe malice and hatred between them and the Gentry; but rather to knit and unite them more faſt together, and the late KING <hi>CAARLES</hi> in his Declaration in the aforeſaid Book of Declarations, page 768, 769. Confeſſes and averrs, That the <hi>LAW</hi> makes the meaneſt Subject as much a <hi>LORD,</hi> of his own as much as the greateſt Peere to be valued, and conſidered as by the ſaid ſeveral Declatations will fully and largly (upon peruſal) appear.</p>
            <p>So that I have ſhewed ſome of the chief FOUNDATIONS of our Government, which is unchangeable. and which all perſonal authorities are ſubſervient unto (their greateſt duty and care being to preſerve the ſame inviolable) and the People will be miſerable if theſe FOUNDATIONS or any ſuitable ſuperſtructure to this FOUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DATIONAL RIGHT, Government or Freedom be changed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>III.</label> As to your third Aphoriſm, you would have done well to have informed the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> wherein, or in what parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars the Government by Lawes formerly in the time of Monarchy were imperfect, or ineffectual, that ſo they might have had ſome benefit by you, by being made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to know what you mean, and how to redreſſe any Invaſion upon our FUNDA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTAL RIGHTS, but a general Charge (in the judgement of Law or Reaſon) ſignifies nothing according to an apptoved Maxim in Law, <hi>Doloſus verſatur in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>IIII.</label> As to your fourth Aphoriſm, It hath been the Peoples miſery that there hath been ſo many various Governments (as you call them) by Arms. But the uſe of Arms in a generally profeſſed and pretended, Chriſtian and rational Common-wealth, that hath ſuch excellent Laws (as we have) muſt be only as contingent things and ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to the Supream Government the FUNDAMENTAL LAWS of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Peace, and Safety, &amp; <hi>PARLIAMENTARY</hi> conſtant <hi>COUNSELS</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:167144:5"/>
            <p>
               <label>V.</label> As to your 5th Aphoriſm, Its hard to judge and averr, that the People cannot ſee as well as feel, and it is much if the loſſe of many thouſand perſons and Families (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral waies) Millions of Treaſure, Deſtruction of Trade, and all other ſad inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and conſequences thereof, ſhould not make them ſee. Indeed, if you had ſaid that a party of the People whoſe eys have ſwelled with fatneſs, and have had more than heart can well or reaſonably wiſh, and who have had great and continual places of profit in the Common-wealth, under every Power almoſt For theſe not to ſee becauſe they have not felt, I ſhould have more approved of ſuch a kind of Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm.</p>
            <p>
               <label>VI.</label> To your ſixth Political Aphoriſm I ſay, That the declared end of this late ſad inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine War, was that we might have our peaceable Government by Laws, abhorring all things of Force; The GOVERNMENT by good Laws (as ours are) is juſt, peaceable, and certain. The Government by FORCE, cannot properly be called a GOVERNMENT, but ought to be ſubſervient to the Supream <hi>Fundamental Law,</hi> and to the Supream peaceable <hi>PARLIAMENTARY</hi> Legiſlators or CONSER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VATORS of that Law.</p>
            <p>
               <label>VII.</label> To the ſeventh Aphoriſm, I ſay in agreement with you, That it is every FREE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BORN mans duty whatſoever, to endeavour to attain to that righteous end the Government by LAWS.</p>
            <p>
               <label>VIII, IX. X, XI, XII, XIII.</label> To the 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. I ſay in brief, What the People of <hi>England</hi> may do, if not truſted with their Rights, I know not: or if truſted, I know not, I cannot divine. I think it is only known to the infinite wiſe God, who foreſees all events; But I have ſhewed you that our Laws are ſufficient, And by a <hi>Fundamental Constitution,</hi> and as a lawful means to preſerve our Rights, it is our Right to have our conſtant <hi>SUCCESSION</hi> of <hi>PARLIAMENTS,</hi> 1 Rem. of Parliament 15. <hi>Dec.</hi> 1641. The Parliament declared. That the Triennial Parliament for the matter of it did not extend to ſo much as by LAW they ought to have required, there being two Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes ſtill in force for a Parliament to be once a year. And the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in the 4th part of his <hi>Institutes,</hi> treating of the High Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> cites 36 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. cap. 10. A Parliament every year, 4 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. cap. <hi>Inter Leges Edgar</hi> Cap. 5. Before rhe Conqueſt <hi>Parliaments</hi> were to be holden twice every year. Sithence good men are rare, and alſo ſithence you ſay, it is not Prudence to be ſure of Aſſemblies of good men, and that there is but a poſſibility of good in a perſonal ſecurity, a Conſtant Succeſſion of Parliaments would be a <hi>LAWFUL</hi> means to make men good, if it were to be ſuppoſed, or uncharitably to be preſumed not to be in conſcience and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; yet for fear of the evil, and infamy that may enſue to themſelves if they ſhould deſtroy good Laws, and make bad ones. So that I hope that it is clear, The
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:167144:6"/>nature of our form is good, and that it will require neceſſary action and uſe, and I ſuppoſe your 13th doth conclude with my opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> Where the SECURITY is in the PERSONS the GOVERNMENT maketh good men EVIL: where the SECURITY is in the FORM the GOVERNMENT ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth evil men GOOD, (eſpecially if the good Law or Form hath its courſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violent interruption or Fraud) <hi>Hazael</hi> had a good opinion of himſelf 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.12, 13. when he asked the weeping Prophet, <hi>Is thy ſervant a Dog that he ſhould do this great thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>XIIII, XV, XVI, XVII, XVIII.</label> To your 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. Aphoriſms I agree, That Aſſemblie legitimatly ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the People, are the only party that can govern without an Army, and that the People are deceived by Names, and not by things, and that the People are generally ſatisfied in a well ordered Common-wealth, and where they are juſtly diſſatisfied it runs to confuſion, and the ſad conſequences thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XIX.</label> To your 19 Aphoriſm, It were good you ſhould endeavour to convince the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parties of <hi>England,</hi> wherein they hold any thing inconſiſtent with the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, that ſo they may know what you meane. That a GOVERNMENT to be mannaged by a few or a party, is inconſiſtent with a Common-wealth, I agree with you in this, for it is contrary to our ancient FUNDAMENTAL CONSTITU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, Lord <hi>Coke</hi> in his 4th part of his <hi>Institutes,</hi> upon his treating of the HIGH COURT of PARLIAMENT I, 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. M. 70. The high Court of PARLIAMENT to be committed to a few, is againſt the Dignity of a Parliament, and no ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ought to be granted.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXI, XXII.</label> To your 21 &amp; 22 Aphoriſms, It ſeems to me ſtrange, that after all this blood and miſery you ſhould plead for a National Religion or Miniſtery, and to hold That any GOVERNMENT without it, is inconſiſtent with a Common-weale; If your meaning be that the Magiſtrate, or any of the People, may give a publick voluntary indowment to any, out of their own Labours, Proprieties, and Eſtates, I conceive they have that Liberty becauſe they have a Liberty of their own Conſcience, and ſo the Magiſtracy may have an Inſpection into the Miniſtery, they being voluntarily (and according to their judgment and Conſcience) obliged one to the other, and ſo it is the MAGISTRATES MINISTERY; But if you mean that a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſhall impoſe a National Religion, and indowment upon the People or upon any conſciencious diſſenting part, when no man can juſtly give ſuch a Power to the Magiſtracy, to Lord it over his Conſcience (which is tender) and to have dominion over his underſtanding (which is only ſubordinate to God in point of Worſhip.) I am not of your judgment. For that if the People, or any of the People ſhall be ſo void of Reaſon, to pretend to give it, they pretend to give what is not in their Power to give, and the Magiſtrate receives a pretended power which is unlawful, inconvenient and diſtracting to receive, and indeed impoſſible (in manifold conſiderations) to be well and peacably mannaged if it were given, or received, or uſurped, (by its being
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:167144:6"/>not given, as indeed it is not in FUNDAMENTAL LAW or Reaſon) Therefore how barbarous, and irrational, as well as unchriſtian it is for a <hi>MAGISTRATE</hi> that is mutable in his underſtanding (as moſt Ages and times have ſhewed) &amp; not <hi>LORD</hi> of his OWN CONSCIENCE: (no more then any other man) to impoſe upon another in Worſhip or charge that which is againſt his Spirit, when the very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and impoſition (if againſt Conſcience) may cauſe the ſin of Hypocriſie, and make the Spirit boyl and riſe in unpeaceableneſs within himſelf againſt the Worſhip, and Form thereof, as well as againſt the perſon impoſed, there being nothing but indiſpoſition of mind both to Perſon, Doctrine, Faith and mutual ſociety, Whereas the reverend Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>VVhatſoever is not of Faith is ſin.</hi> And God himſelf doth not value a worſhip if in Hypocriſie and without Faith, and conviction; I might men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the miſerable and great calamity the endeavours of impoſition upon the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath occaſioned, How grievious and burthenſome were the waies thereof (decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red publickly to be offered) by the Biſhops to men of different Judgments who came to be diſtinguiſhed by <hi>Presbyter, &amp;c.</hi> What calamities did they declare to ſuffer? And what change of calamity came upon the flouriſhing <hi>Epiſcopacy?</hi> And how grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and contrary was it (a great while (and peradventure yet ſtill remains) to the Conſcience of the <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> to ſubject to the Judgment, Form and Worſhip of the <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and how difficult hath it proved to the <hi>Presbyter</hi> to endeavour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle with matters that concern the Conſcience or Reaſon of any other men different from themſelves, I ſubmit to your ſelf, and ingenuous and impartial Readers, Beſides, if you take a view of the whole body of the Scriptures of the new Teſtament you will find that the greateſt part of the National Miniſtery, and the ſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles of God, and of Chriſt were for the moſt part contrary one to the other; and how that God by his Son Chriſt, and his ſaid ſpecial Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets brands them with words of infamy, as grand and capital inſtigators to Kings &amp; Princes, by adviſing them to ſhew their advantage &amp; beoppreſſive to their great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, cares, and trouble of mind, perplexity of State and ſometimes deſolation, aſwel as the calamity of multitudes of good People, and effuſion of innocent blood. And indeed in our late times, Mr. <hi>Bagſhawe</hi> in his Argument of Law in Parliament (againſt the Biſhops Cannons) averreth, That the Liberty of Conſcience is comprehended in the Charter of our Liberties. And I alſo remember, I have read that the <hi>Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> petitioning <hi>Jovianus</hi> the Emperour, for baniſhing of thoſe who were not of their judgement in matters of their Religion; The Emperour peruſing their Supplication gave them no other anſwer but this, I tell you trvely I cannot away with contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſuch as do imbrace Unity and Concord, I do honour and reverence them: And I have alſo read, that it was the ſaying of <hi>Maximilianus</hi> the Emperour, To ſeek to domineer over the Conſcience, is impudently to invade the Tower of Heaven; And how inconſiſtent it is with that golden Rule, (which every man ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour actually to excel another in, according to the ſaying of the Heathen Orator, <hi>Omnis virtutis laus in actione conſistit,</hi> the praiſe of all vertue conſiſts in action) 7 <hi>Matt.</hi> 12. <hi>VVhatſoever things you would have others do to you, do the ſame to them,</hi> 7 <hi>Matt.</hi> 2. <hi>Judge not that ye be not judged, with what meaſure you mete, it ſhall be met to you again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Alexander Hinderſon</hi> (the great <hi>Scot</hi>) in his Paper to the late King <hi>Charles</hi> about 1646. hath this quotation I remember (ſaith he) that the famous <hi>Joannes Picus Mirandula</hi> proveth by irrefragable reaſons, which no rational man will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:167144:7"/>contradict, that no man hath ſo much power over his own underſtanding, as to make himſelf beleeve what he will, or to think that to be true which his own reaſon telleth him is falſe; much leſs is it poſſible for any man to have his reaſon commanded by the will or pleaſure of another. And further he confeſſed, That,</p>
            <p>It is a true ſaying of the Shoolmen; <hi>Voluntas imper at intellectui, quoad exerciti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um non quod ſpecificationem,</hi> Mine own will or the will of another may command me to think upon a matter; but no will or command, can conſtrain me to determine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then my reaſon teacheth me. See alſo Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> his Chriſtian Concertation as to this point of Chriſt, his being King and Lord of the Conſcience, and Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> his Healing queſtion, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. therefore let me cloſe up my opinion againſt your 21 Aphoriſm, with the force of your own words in your 22 Aphoriſm, <hi>(viz.) To hold that there may be Liberty of Conſcience, and not Liberty of Conſcience is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſistent with a Commonwealth that hath the Liberty of her own Conſcience, or that is not Popiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>XXIII, XXIV, XXV.</label> As to your 23, 24, 25. Aphoriſmes I agree with you, that where civil liberty is intire, it includes liberty of Conſcience, and where liberty of Conſcience is intire, it includes civil liberty; They are the inſeparable RIGHT of the people. As to your 25th. Liberty of conſcience muſt have ſecurity under any <hi>GOVERNMENT;</hi> or elſe the oppoſers thereof wil deſcend into an inevitable Tyranny.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXVI.</label> To your 26th. Aphoriſm I have cited and declared unto you the great and chief Foundations of our Government, which are GOOD ANCIENT LAWS, and SUC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CESSIVE PARLIAMENTS; ſo that you need not put your ſelf to the danger of introducing Government, or waving Prudence, and committing things to chance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXVII.</label> To your 27th. Aphoriſm, I ſhall onely ſay in addition to what I have already ſaid, That our aforeſaid Fundamental Laws, &amp; Government of England, made and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med legally by our good and peaceable Anceſtors, goeth Univerſally upon natural principles, and ſo is not inconſiſtent with Scriptures, the ſaid laws of England are grounded upon the Laws of God and Nature Doctor and Student, and Fineux and Priſet former chief Juſtices in England (in the dayes of Monarchy) ſaid the Laws of England are founded upon the laws of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXVIII.</label> To your 28th. Aphoriſm I agree, that the wiſdom of man in the Formation of humane Government, may not go upon ſupernatural principles, becauſe they are inconſiſtent with a Commonwealth, upon many and divers conſiderations, too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and too impertinent at preſent to treat of, conſidering we have ſuch righteous Fundamentals already laid, better then which we none can lay, which foundations no men upon any pretence can juſtly deſtroy.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXIX.</label> To your 29th. Aphoriſm wherein you aver and ſay in theſe words. <hi>viz.</hi> To hold that (Hirelings as they are termed by ſome) or an indowed Miniſtry to be removed out of the Church is in-conſiſtent with a Commonwealth. I conceive I have ſufficiently anſwered this in anſwer to your 21, 22, 23, 24. Aphoriſmes wherein the people have their lawful liberty, and the endowed Miniſtry have their lawfull liberty to receive
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:167144:7"/>the Contribution (if voluntary) of either Magiſtracie or others, and to expect more is a violent impoſition and intrenchment, upon the natural and Chriſtian Rights of the People, which judgement I confeſs I ſhall be of, unleſs I ſhall be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally ſatisfied in anſwer to what <hi>I</hi> have already ſaid; and unleſs it can be alſo made appear to me, that the incomparable PERSON CHRIST, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did aduiſe Magiſtracie, to compel pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſons to violent actions to conſtrain maintenance to them, or any other of their ſucceſſive Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtry, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Chriſt bids his Apoſtles preach to the Loſt Sheep of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them freely to give becauſe they had freely received; and orders them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to provide Gold, nor Silver, nor Braſs in their Purſes, nor ſcrip for their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, nor two Coats, nor Shooes, nor ſtaffe, and if the Houſe, City, or Town, was not worthy or ſhould not receive them or hear their Word, they were to depart, and ſhake the duſt off their feet, agreeing with <hi>Luke</hi> 9.2, 3. and <hi>Luke</hi> 10.3, 4. He told them he ſent them as <hi>Lambs</hi> amongſt <hi>VVolves,</hi> and to the end they (in their loving and <hi>Christian</hi> kind nature, as examples for others) might not ſcruple eating and drinking ſuch things as were freely ſet before them. They were approved in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting thereof, becauſe the Labourer is worthy of his hire. And 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Paul</hi> commends the Churches of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> that they were willing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be bountiful, and to make intreaty to the Apoſtle for his acceptance of their liberality, and yet not as he hoped for it, He was ſo far from uſing arguments or FORCE and Violence to Magiſtracie inducing them to compel others to their ſubſiſtency. And I muſt confeſs if you can prove that the indowed Miniſtry at this day (many of whom are Learned and Wiſe men) can ſafely intitle themſelves to be the Lineal deſcent, and eſpecial Miniſtry of Chriſt, yet it will ſtill remain to prove that they can legally extend their Authority, or deſire the Sword of Magiſtracie to extend his ſtrength higher or in another way, or method, (upon any pretence or diſpenſation) then either Chriſt or his Apoſtles did: I preſume there may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a thouſand-fold more reaſon and Evangelical apparent arguments (againſt ſuch an Innovation) then for it.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXX. XXXI.</label> To your 30, &amp; 31, Aphoriſms <hi>(viz.)</hi> That nature is of God, and that ſome part in every Religion is Natural, You ſhould explain your ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how it may be ſaid to bee of God, and what part in every Religion is Natural; if you would have another know your Judgment, and be convinced by you; In order to which I ſhall commend unto you an excellent little Treatiſe, entituled <hi>Natures Vindication,</hi> by Capt. <hi>Robert Euerard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXII, XXXIII.</label> To theſe Aphoriſms I agree at preſent, That an univerſal effect demonſtrateth or may demonſtrate an Univerſal Cauſe, there being a Reaſon for it in your 33 Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Univerſal Cauſe is Nature it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <label>XXXIIII. XXXV, XXXVI, XXXVII, XXXVIII, XXXIX, XL.</label> 
               <hi>I</hi> agree to the 34, That every man hath ſome ſenſe of Religion in him (if you mean by it, an acknowledgement of God, which is preſumed to be in his underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) and for your 35, <hi>I</hi> ſhall not diſagree to it, if the rational Principle be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, upon colour or pretence of Religion; For your 36, I agree with you, That Government is of humane prudence, and humane Prudence is adequate unto mans
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:167144:8"/>nature; But humane Prudence and mans nature, will never deſtroy a Legal ancient Government of a Nation, (grounded upon humane Prudence, and the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (as ours is) For your 37, A Prudential Government (if you mean by Prudence, true Wiſdom) cannot be regardleſs of true Religion; for thereby it would be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfactory unto mans nature; But yet on the other hand, there may be a Religion National or Publick, or a Publick leading, (terms in your 39, 40, &amp; 41 Aphoriſms) That may be directly againſt God, Law, Nature and Nation. As to your 39, It doth not prove, or infer a publick leading in Religion to be good, becauſe the Major part of Mankind, giveth up it ſelf unto it, and therefore you had no reaſon to make ſuch an Aphoriſm as your 40th, wherein you ſay, There muſt be a National Religion, that there may be a Publick leading, Witneſs the daies of Q. <hi>Mary, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>XLI. XLII. XLIII, XLIIII. XLV. XLVI.</label> 
               <hi>I</hi> agree with yovr 41, &amp; 42 taking what <hi>I</hi> have already ſaid in this Point before and what you have already granted in your 22, 23, 24, Aphoriſms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That if either Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor or Minor part in a Nation, deprives the others of Liberty of Conſcience, it is Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny. To your 43, &amp; 44, The great pretence of the National Miniſtery is, That they are Miniſters of Chriſt, and not relating to the Prieſthood before Chriſt: ſo that to endeavour to attain to maintainance by Violence and Impoſition, is againſt that Chriſtian Apoſtolical example. And as for aboliſhing the <hi>Nationall</hi> Religion, none can or ought to endeavour to do that but the National Magiſtracy if he ſee Juſt cauſe, becauſe they are the Magiſtrates particular indowed Miniſtery, the Magiſtrate having the liberty of his own Conſcience, So that there is no rational Foundation, for the unconverted <hi>Jews</hi> (your own terms) to take away the Liberty of Conſcience from Chriſtians, For equal Juſtice and Conſcience being obſerved, there would be no diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing one another; Therefore if you are for ſuch an impartiall Liberty of Conſcience, you may have ſuch a National Religion or endowed Clergy.</p>
            <p>I though to have treated more upon this ſubject, but <hi>I</hi> leave it to ſome other occaſion, only I ſhall commend unto you the excellent Treatiſe of <hi>John Osborne</hi> Eſquire, in his <hi>Book</hi> called <hi>an Indictment against Tythes,</hi> or <hi>Tythes no VVages for Goſpel Ministers,</hi> (which is a Title pretended to in theſe times) which <hi>Book</hi> was Printed for <hi>Livewel Chapman</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Popes-head</hi> Alley <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>XLVII, XLVIII, XLIX, L. LI, LII, LIII, LIIII, LV, LVI, LVII, LVIII, LIX, LX,</label> To all theſe particulars, I only ſay in ſhort, they are things determinable by <hi>SU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PREAM PARLIAMENTARY COUNCELS,</hi> and our Nation is built upon the Foundations of Juſt Laws, and Liberties already, and our ſtedfaſtneſs unto that would be a means to promote our welfare, and ſave us from deſtruction; but to tell us of any thing that ſavours of Innovation, of the Preſidents of the <hi>Athenians</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> or the <hi>Uinted Provinces, &amp;c,</hi> can be no more pleaſing or ſafe to us, then (I conceive) it would be pleaſing to them for us to foment Innovation amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>LXI, <hi>to the</hi> CXX.</label> To theſe I onely ſay, that I know not what Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> (if he had prevailed) would have done or introduced, whether a Commonwealth or a King, I leave it to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:167144:8"/>thoſe that were privy to it, and to his Council (if any.) But if Monarchy ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be reſtored, I beleeve it would find a great inevitable incumbrance and affliction to it ſelf, if it ſhould Govern without LAWS and PARLIAMENTS. For it is no pleaſant thing to Govern by Armes, neither to the GOVERNOURS or GOVERNMENED and if the Fundamental Laws and <hi>Constant Parliaments</hi> be not obſerved inviolable the people are miſerable, and the common intereſt of the the people will be laid aſide inevitably, and we ſhall thereby fully declare, That we will fully ſlight and undervalue that peace and tranquillty that we may poſſeſs as ſome fruit of that blood and treaſure which hath been conſumed in this Nation. So that I ſay and averre by the requirable juſt application of your <hi>XCII</hi> Aphoriſme, to lay aſide our Fundamental Laws and CONSTANT conſtitution of PARLIAMENTS (as moſt probable Conſervators of our <hi>FUNDAMENTALS.</hi>) <hi>VVe leave our our ſelves and our Posterity to a further purchaſe of that which we may preſtntly injoy, and hereafter leave to our Posterity in peace and glory,</hi> not to be taken away from them. As our <hi>Ancestors</hi> have left them unto us not to be taken away from us. I hope I have already proved that the <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of this Nation is ſo juſt and of known, and approved good in the injoyment whereof neither Monarchy Ariſtocracie, or Democracy can juſtly hurt us, by any invention, or judgement. And although you ſay in your <hi>CXVII</hi> Aphoriſm, That it is not below the Dignity of the greateſt Aſſembly, but according to the practiſe of the beſt Commonwealths, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any man that is able to propoſe to them for the good of his Country, Yet I conceive it is not convenient for a Supream Legiſlative Councel to admit any man wilfully to propoſe any thing (apparently Innovating) to ſubvert a <hi>Fundamental Law</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> many having (upon peaceable and prudent judgement of our <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors</hi>) been highly diſcouraged therein and felt their indignation, as I have already urged and proved.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rechabites</hi> obedience may be applyed (as I conceive) in this caſe, who were commended of God for denying his Prophet to drink Wine, becauſe their father com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to the contrary. Although the Record ſaith, The WORD came unto <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> FROM THE LORD, in the days of <hi>Jehoiakim,</hi> ſon of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> King of <hi>Judah;</hi> ſaying: <hi>Go to the houſe of the</hi> Rechabites, <hi>and ſpeak to them, and bring them into the houſe of the LORD, into one of the Chambers, and GIVE them VVINE to drink,</hi> Jer. 35.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 18, 19, <hi>verſes.</hi> And indeed if we ſhould admit Innovations upon our <hi>FUNDAMENTAL LAVVS</hi> received as <hi>I</hi> have ſaid before, from our <hi>Ancestors,</hi> we ſhould make an illegal Preſident to ſubject our ſelves, not onely to the deſtruction of the good being of them, but to a thouſand other Innovations, as often as the <hi>Moon</hi> changes, or occaſions, or diſcontents, ariſe, or power prevails, or as often as any perſon or perſons whatſoever may ſuggeſt, whereby to introduce an inevitable dangerous <hi>ARBITRARY POVVER,</hi> contrary to all the Declarations, Promiſes, Vows, and pretences, and what the conſequences of that may be, lyes one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the breaſt of the Almighty.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Innovation</hi> it ſelf, (if by any party) contrary to a FUNDAMENTAL LAW is ARBITRARY. And Arbitrarineſs is contrary to NATURE, LAW, AND PEACE.</p>
            <p>The PARLIAMENTS long Remonſtrance of Grieviances 16 <hi>Dec.</hi> 1641, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated the <hi>PETITION of RIGHT</hi> in full Parliament, Counſelled the People againſt Arbitrary Power, violating the Law, and breaking the Priveledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, calling it a bold and preſumptious Injuſtice of ſuch Miniſters, as durſt break th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:167144:9"/>Laws, and ſuppreſs the Liberties, The Book of Declarations printed by <hi>Edward Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hands,</hi> &amp; <hi>page</hi> 484. The Parliament declared themſelves offended that the Kings par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did endeavour to poſſeſs the people that they intended to take away the Law, and introduce an Arbitrary Government, a thing which every honeſt morall man ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrs (ſay they) much more the Wiſdom, Juſtice and Piety of both Houſes of parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And <hi>page</hi> 709, It is well known, ſay they, The Laws of holding <hi>PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS</hi> once a year LAY ASLEEP for a long time, yet the practiſe was NO ARGUMENT AGAINST the <hi>RIGHT.</hi> And <hi>pag.</hi> 574, 575. They complained, That the Kings party were laying a Foundation of an <hi>ARBITRARY GOVERN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the late <hi>KING CHARLES</hi> his Declaration <hi>pag.</hi> 768, 769. are words to this effect, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the RULES of an unlimited <hi>ARBITRARY POWER,</hi> are inconſiſtent with the leaſt pretence or ſhaddow of that property it ſeems to defend. And in the ſaid <hi>KING CHARLES</hi> his Speech and Proteſtation made 19 <hi>Sept.</hi> 1642, <hi>page</hi> 614 are theſe words <hi>(viz.) I</hi> do promiſe in the preſence of Almighty God, and as <hi>I</hi> hope for his bleſſing and protection, &amp;c. To maintain the <hi>JUST PRIVILEDGE</hi> and <hi>FREEDOM</hi> of <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> and to Govern by the known Lawes of the Land to my utmoſt Power, and particularly to obſerve inviolably the Lawes conſented unto by me this <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Book of the Armies Declarations <hi>page</hi> 38, in 1647, Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they were not a meer mercinary Army, to ſerve an <hi>ARBITRARY POWER</hi> of State, That they took up Arms in Judgment and Conſcience, for their own and the Peoples juſt Rights and Liberties, To aſſert and vindicate the Juſt Power, and Rights of the People in Parliament, againſt all <hi>ARBITRARY</hi> Power, violence, and Oppreſſion againſt all particular parties or intereſts whatſoever. And <hi>pag.</hi> 41, That they could not wiſh to have an <hi>ARBITRARY POVVER</hi> in any in whom they, more confided, or who were moſt of their oipinon or Principles, or whom they might have moſt perſonal aſſurance of, or intereſt in. <hi>I</hi> have read that when <hi>Baſſianus</hi> had ſlain his Brother, and Coemperour <hi>Geta</hi> in his Mothers Arms, he intreated <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinianus</hi> a famous Lawyer to plead his excuſe, whoſe noble anſwer was, and is to be be commended, <hi>(viz.) Non tam facile est excuſare quam facere fratricidium;</hi> It is not ſo eaſie to excuſe, as to commit a fratricide, ſo <hi>I</hi> may ſay in this Caſe, It may be eaſier to endeavour and to introduce a hundred Innovations then to juſtifie one.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>I</hi> have given you my thoughts of your Aphoriſms, in general intending to your own ſatisfaction (as well as others, and the diſcharge of my own Conſcience) For ſome things which <hi>I</hi> conceive do chieſly belong to <hi>PARLIAMENTARY COVNCIL I</hi> wholly omit; But only in love to my Countrey (in which <hi>I</hi> have bin 11 years a very great ſufferer) <hi>I</hi> put in my mite, without intended diſreſpect to you (you being a ſtranger to me) And ſo <hi>I</hi> ſhall cocnlude with ſubſcribing my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>24 <hi>Octob.</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your friend and Country-man. <hi>W. BRAY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
